INSTRUCTOR: Hello, everyone,
and welcome to the content video
for the quicksort.
OK, now that you
know the merge sort,
the quicksort is even
a little bit faster,
of an n log n sorting algorithm.
It's similar to the
merge sort, in that it
uses divide and conquer
and that it uses recursion.
Meaning, it splits up the list
into smaller parts, sorts them,
and then returns them
back into the larger
list, which is now sorted.
But it's a little bit
different than the merge sort.
The merge sort, by comparison,
divides up the list
into buckets of size 1
and then merges them back
into a sorted list.
From the top-down, it goes top,
the top being the unsorted list,
divides it down into
buckets of size 1,
and then merges them back
up into a sorted list.
Well, the quicksort,
it actually--
just think of it from that
top-down approach again.
It sorts as it goes down, so it
doesn't-- by the time it divides
everything up,
it's done sorting.
And it does that using a pivot.
So here's how the pivot works.
A pivot is a number in the list.
And what basically
happens is things
are moved around in the
list so that everything
that's smaller than the
pivot goes on the left.
Everything that's right--
that's larger than the pivot
goes on the right.
And so then once you're
done moving everything
around the pivot, you haven't
sorted the entire list.
You've only sorted
everything based on a pivot.
Smaller than the
pivot on the left.
Greater than the
pivot on the right.
Well, then this is where the
power of recursion comes in.
If I know everything on the
left is smaller than the pivot,
then that's my new
sublist to sort.
It's still unsorted, but
it's much smaller now.
I take the new smaller than
the pivot list and call
quicksort on that list.
And I do that again and
again until the entire list
is broken down into pieces
that are sorted now.
So let's take a look on
how to do that on the board
and then I'll show you
the code after that.
There we go.
OK, the quicksort.
So I select a pivot.
And there's a few different
ways to select a pivot,
but it really doesn't matter.
I'm going to use the one
that the code you're going
to see in a second uses,
which is, basically
just pick the number on
the right as our pivot.
OK, so there is our pivot.
Now what I'm going to
do is anything smaller
than 6, our pivot, is
going to be moved over
to the right of it.
And everything smaller is going
to be moved over to the left.
So I keep track of the
spot just adjacent to the 6
because I'm going to
use it for swapping.
And then I go down and
look, is 2 smaller than 6?
Yes, leave it alone.
Is 9 smaller than 6?
No, then swap it so that it
is now right of the pivot.
So I keep track of
the spot next to it.
6 gets moved there, 9 gets
moved over, and 2 is there.
So I keep track of the spot
to the left and my pivot
and put anything
larger to the right.
OK, I keep moving.
Is 2 smaller?
Yep.
Is 5 smaller?
Yes.
1, 4, 1, 3, yes.
Then we're done.
OK now, it's true,
though, that this
over here to the right of
the pivot, if it's size one,
it's also sorted.
So I have a pivot
and a 9 of size 1.
This is now sorted.
So I've sorted a big chunk
of it here using a pivot,
even though I have not
sorted the entire list,
but I recurse and do it again.
So now, when I say
I recurse, here's
the new list I'm going to sort
because 6 and 9 is already
sorted.
Here's the list
I'm going to sort.
So my new pivot is now 2.
And I need to go
through and make sure
that everything smaller
than 2 is on the left.
Everything larger than
2 is on the right.
OK, so I do that by
keeping track of this spot,
then I'm going to be
used for swapping.
Is 5 greater than 2?
Yes, it is.
I'm going to swap them.
And that's my pivot.
OK, is 1 less than 2?
Yes, you can leave it there.
Is 4 less than 2?
No, I'm going to swap it.
So keep track of the
spot to the left.
So this 4, 1, 2 is going to
get moved around as 1, 2, 4.
Keeping track that
that is still my pivot.
1 and 1 less than 2, good.
Leave them there.
3 is not.
3 is greater so we're
going to move it.
So my spot to the left and
the 2 get swapped around.
So it becomes 3, 2, and this 1.
There we go.
OK, so there's my pivot.
So now I've got my list.
I've got my list smaller
than the pivot, 1, 1.
I've got my list 3, 4, and 5.
So now I've got this list.
I recurse down.
I'm going to draw a black line
there to show I recurse down.
But when you have
a list of size--
let's do this.
A pivot and list the
size 1, I know, OK,
that's not greater
than the pivot.
I leave it alone and I'm done.
Then I know that this is done.
So look at the
chunks that are done.
The 1, the 1, the 2, and
then the 6 and the 9.
So then this one becomes
my next list to sort.
5 is my new pivot.
I'll move it down.
4 and 3 are already smaller.
That looks good.
So now I recurse down.
4 and 3.
4 is my new pivot.
3 is already smaller than
4 and it's on the left.
I'm good and I'm done.
So now, if you're
thinking, well, you
didn't divide down and conquer,
you didn't merge the buckets
and move things
around, that's actually
the power of the quicksort.
If you just keep
track of your pivots,
recurse down, move around the
numbers based on the pivot,
by the time you get
down to list of size 1,
you've already moved everything
around based on pivots,
and it's all sorted.
So the going down represents
the recursive calls.
The blue lines
represent our pivots.
Look at our list now.
1, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 9.
Is that sorted?
Yes, it is.
And there's no process of
iterating back up like there
is in the merge sort.
All right, so we
divide and conquer,
that gives us our log n.
We go through the
comparisons, that's our n.
The quicksort is a big
O notation of n log n.
All right, so let's look
at the code, how it works.
Here we go.
OK, so the quicksort.
Let me start with the recursive.
So the quicksort is recursive.
I keep track of here's my
array, the list I'm sorting.
And then I have my
low and high numbers.
These are indexes in the list.
So as I recurse
down, low and high
are going to change to what
point in the list I am,
but it's always going to get
smaller, smaller, and smaller,
and smaller until
we get to our base
case here of the length of the
array as 1, then we return.
All right, so now I
need to partition.
This partition
function basically
just takes everything
smaller than the pivot,
moves it on the left,
everything greater than that,
moves it on the right.
So once I've done
this step on line 33,
once I've moved everything
based on the pivot,
now I know I just recurse
down using the quicksort.
Everything on the left of
the pivot, I recurse down.
Everything on the right of
the pivot, I recurse down,
and then I come back up
here and do it again.
And the only thing I'm
moving around each time
is everything based on a pivot.
So let's go look at partition
and see how that works.
All right, so the partition
function, we select our pivot,
which, again, as I
mentioned, is just
we're going to select the
item that's on the right.
Then we're going to
loop through and just
move everything that's
smaller than the pivot
to the left of it,
and swap it around.
So by the time we're
done, everything
smaller than the pivot is
on the left, everything
greater than the pivot is
on the right, and we return.
That's all it does.
We partition.
Once we partition, we know
everything on the left
is smaller.
Recurse down on that.
We know everything to the
right of the pivot is greater.
We recurse down on that.
Until we get down to the size
of size 1 and we're done.
Quicksort.
Give it a run and--
hang on.
And there it is.
Let me-- in fact, let
me move back our--
let's get our list.
Same list we did on the board.
There we go.
And ta-da, quicksort.
Quicksort is used today.
It is fast.
I think Python uses a
combination of quicksort or--
you have to Google
me on this one.
Uses a combination
of a couple of sorts.
But the divide and conquer
and log n of quicksort
is definitely used today.
And that divide
and conquer piece,
the recursing down piece is what
gets you that n log n over the n
squared algorithms
that I showed you.
OK, this concludes the content
video for the quicksort.
Thanks for watching.